Arents Christmas Card Collection
Arents Christmas Card Collection
1891-1974
Arents, George, 1875-1960.
2.25 linear ft.
Collection of Christmas cards accumulated by George and Lena Arents, featuring notable figures from American arts and letters.
3178208
Biographical History
George Arents, Jr. (1875-1960) was an American businessman. He studied at Columbia University and received his master's degree from Syracuse University at the age of 57. His father and great-uncle were founders of the Allen & Ginter Tobacco Company, which later became the American Tobacco Company. In 1922 Arents became a director of the American Tobacco Company and from 1924 he was the treasurer of both the American Machine and Foundry and International Cigar Machinery. He was also a collector of books and other published material relating to tobacco. He and his wife Lena made substantial gifts to Syracuse University; in recognition of their generosity, the department of rare books and special collections at Bird Library was for many years known as the George Arents Research Library.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Arents Christmas Card Collection consists of an extensive collection of Christmas cards, most featuring important figures from American letters, sent by and to George and Lena Arents. Subjects include Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Algernon Swinburne, Gertrude Stein, Charles Dickens, and Henry David Thoreau. In some cases, the designer, typographer, and/or printer are given.
Arrangement of the Collection
Subdivided into those sent by the Arentses and those sent to them. Within each series, items are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also the
Arents Grand Tour Collection
and the
Arents Postcard Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Publishing, printing and book arts; Art -- Illustrators; Arents, George, 1875-1960.; Arents, Lena.; Authors, American.; Christmas cards -- Collectors and collecting.; Christmas cards -- Specimens.; Poets, American.; Christmas cards.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of George and Lena Arents.
Inventory
- Sent by the Arentses
  - E. B. Browning, letter to Napoleon III re. Victor Hugo, 1932; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Edward Fitzgerald, "A Country Carol", 1937 (Box 1)
  - Dickens, Three Passages, 1938?; 5 copies (Box 1)
  - Longfellow, "The Arrow and the Song", 1939?; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes, "Army Hymn", 1940; 5 copies (Box 1)
  - Story of the Hymn "America", 1941; 6 copies (Box 1)
  - Gibbons, "We Are Coming Father Abraham", 1942; 6 copies (Box 1)
  - Field, "How the Good Knight Attended upon..., 1943; 5 copies (Box 1)
  - Samuel Fillmore Bennett, "The Sweet By and By", 1944; 6 copies (Box 1)
  - Field, "A Song of the Christmas Wind", 1945; 7 copies (Box 1)
  - Swinburne, "A New Year's Message to Joseph Mazziki", 1946 (Box 1)
  - Chesterton, "A Christmas Song for Three Guilds", 1947; 5 copies (Box 1)
  - Charles Norman, "A Season's Garland", 1948; 6 copies (Box 2)
  - Southwell, "The Nativity of Christ", 1949; 4 copies (Box 2)
  - Swinburne, "In Church", 1950; 2 copies (Box 2)
  - Swinburne "Beyond Church", 1951 (Box 2)
  - Jones, "From Saint Nicholas to Santa Claus", 1952; 5 copies (Box 2)
  - Henry van Dyke, "The Christmas Angel", 1953; 5 copies (Box 2)
  - Greenaway, A Christmas Letter, 1954; 4 copies (Box 2)
  - Ben Buckhurst Chronicle, 1865, 1955; 6 copies (Box 2)
  - Robert Cruikshank, Scenes from the Bible, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Samuel McChord Crothers, "Miss Muffet's Christmas Party", 1957; 3 copies (Box 2)
  - Phillips Brooks, "A Christmas Carol", 1958; 7 copies (Box 2)
  - Christmas in the Days of Good Queen Bess, 1959; 4 copies (Box 2)
- Sent by others
  - Crothers, S.M. Miss Muffett's Christmas Party, 1891 (Box 3)
    printed by Banning Press (St. Paul)
  - Richmond, Grace. On Christmas Day in the Morning, 1908 (Box 3)
    printed by Doubleday, Paige
  - Calkins. E. On the Technique of Being Deaf., 1923 (Box 3)
    sent by Calkins, E.; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - "The Oriental and Captain Palmer", 1925 (Box 3)
    sent by Budd, Ralph; printed by McGill-Warner (St .Paul)
  - Christmas Has Come Back Again, 1925; 2 copies (Box 3)
    sent by Marchbanks; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - Wells, Gabriel, "Life Eternal", 1925 (Box 2)
    sent by Weiss, J.; designer/typographer Rogers, Bruce; printed by Rudge, William Edwin
  - Morris, C, "The Toper's Apology", 1926; 2 copies (Box 3)
  - Broun, Heywood, "A Shepherd", 1926 (Box 3)
    sent by Nelson, G.
  - Wells, Gabriel, "Life Temporal", 1926 (Box 3)
  - Holiday Greetings and Good Wishes, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Klitgaard, Kaj. Map of the Holy Land, 1927 (Box 3)
    sent by Rudge, E; printed by Rudge, William Edwin
  - Wells, Gabriel, "These Three,", 1927 (Box 3)
  - Merry Christmas and Happy New Year, 1930 (Box 3)
  - "The Christmas Spirit", 1930 (Box 3)
    sent by Newton, A.E.; printed by Newton
  - Hal Marchbanks Wishes You Chreeful Holidays, 1931 (Box 3)
  - "A Thomas Hardy Memorial", 1931 (Box 3)
  - Ascot., 1933 (Box 3)
  - Staffordshire, 1935 (Box 3)
  - "My Library", 1936 (Box 3)
    sent by Cheever, L; designer/typographer Rogers, Bruce; printed by Prairie Press
  - "Pope, Poetry and Portrait", 1936 (Box 3)
  - "A Book Collector? How Come?, 1937 (Box 3)
    sent by Cheever, L; printed by Prairie Press
  - De La Mare, W, "A Poem", 1937 (Box 3)
    sent by J, N?
  - Moore, C, "Twas the Night Before Christmas", 1937 (Box 3)
    sent by Rendel, W; designer/typographer Gentry, Helen; printed by Rudge, William Edwin
  - Warde,B.L, "The Shelter in Bedlam", 1937 (Box 3)
    sent by Warde, B.L.; printed by Clark, R.& R. Edinburgh
  - "Schnitzelbank... Sketches by Fritz Kredel", 1938 (Box 3)
    sent by Cary, Melbert; designer/typographer Van Vechten, George; printed by Wooly Whale
  - Baring-Gould, S, "Three Kings Rode from the Orient Land", 1938 (Box 3)
    sent by Drake, James; printed by Rudge, William E. Sons
  - Jones, Dan Burne, "The Least of These," "The Eerie Incident", 1938 (Box 3)
    sent by Jones, Dan; designer/typographer Forgue, Norman W.; printed by Black Cat
  - "George Dyer", 1938 (Box 4)
  - "Like Unto.. ", 1939 (Box 4)
    sent by Kraft, James L.
  - "An Eighteenth Century Greeting... Thomas Bewick, 1940 (Box 4)
    sent by Diamond, E; designer/typographer Diamond, Edouard; printed by Hyacinth Press
  - Horace, "'The Country, That's the Place to Live!'", 1940 (Box 4)
    sent by Macy, George; designer/typographer Macy, Helen; printed by Walpole Printing
  - Shapiro, "Christmas Tree", 1940 (Box 4)
    sent by Shapiro, Karl; printed by Hallmark
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, "Christmas, " Illus. Fritz Kredel., 1940 (Box 4)
  - "Allegory", 1941 (Box 4)
    sent by Vander Poel
  - Winterich, John T, "Clio and My Aunt Bertha", 1942 (Box 4)
  - "A Christmas Letter: Witches and Warlocks", 1943 (Box 4)
    sent by Biddle, Moncure; designer/typographer Gutekunst, Joseph; printed by Buchanan, George H.
  - "Four Connecticut Wood Engravings", 1943 (Box 4)
  - Glover, Florida, "The First Christmas, " Illus. Susanne Suba, 1943 (Box 4)
    designer/typographer Suba, Susanne; printed by Dutton
  - "A Chrismas Letter: Jacques Callot, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Moore, C. "The Night Before Christmas and The Night After Christmas", 1944 (Box 4)
    sent by Diamond, E.; designer/typographer Diamond, Edouard; printed by Hyacinth Press
  - Christmas Greetings ("Collection of Other Men's Christmases"), 1944 (Box 4)
    sent by Richey, F.O.
  - Thoreau, "A Pig Tale", 1947 (Box 4)
    sent by Rogers, Bruce; designer/typographer Rogers, Bruce; printed by Rogers, Bruce
  - Longfellow, "The Building of the Ship, " Engrv. Will Simmons, 1948 (Box 4)
    sent by Diamond, E
  - "Our Lady's Juggler, " Illus. Raymond Lufkin., 1951 (Box 4)
    sent by Lufkin, Raymond
  - "Is There a Santa Claus?", 1952 (Box 4)
  - "Casey at the Bat", 1955 (Box 4)
    sent by Meyers, Eddie; designer/typographer Weiler, Joseph Francis; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - "Christmas Is Coming, " Illus. Lucina Wakefield., 1955 (Box 4)
    sent by Weiler, Betty; designer/typographer Weiler, Joseph Francis; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - Slaughter, L, "The New Northwest, " Orig. 1874., 1956 (Box 4)
    sent by Beineke, F.; printed by Yale University Press
  - Van Dyke, Henry, "Who Owns the Mountains?", 1956; 4 copies (Box 4)
    sent by Wylie, Porter; designer/typographer Weiler, Joseph Francis; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - "Wonderful Narrative of Lieutenant Harrison", 1957 (Box 4)
    sent by Beineke, F.; printed by Yale University Press?
  - Grayson, David, "A Day of Pleasant Bread", 1957; 2 copies (Box 4)
    sent by Weiler, Joseph; designer/typographer Weiler, Joseph Francis; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - "The 51st Chaper of Genesis: A Parable against Persecution", 1958; 2 copies (Box 5)
    sent by Duschnes, Phil
  - "Th: Nast: The Man Who Made Santa Claus", 1958; 2 copies (Box 5)
  - "Father Balthasar Visits the Sinaloa Missions, 1744-1745", 1959 (Box 5)
    sent by Beineke, F.
  - Gould, John, "Ye Olde Fashioned Yule.. ", 1959 (Box 5)
  - "'Old Rough and Ready' Speaks His Mind", 1960 (Box 5)
    sent by Beineke, F.; designer/typographer Rollins, Carl Purington; printed by Yale University Press
  - Anthony, Edward, "A Firm Stand on Santa Claus", 1960; 2 copies (Box 5)
    sent by Marchbanks; designer/typographer Bernfried, Joseph; printed by Marchbanks Press
  - Jefferson, Thomas, "The Education of an Explorer.. ", 1961 (Box 5)
  - Sandoz, Mari, "The Far Looker", 1962; 2 copies (Box 5)
    designer/typographer Sindin, Nedda; printed by Buffalo Head Press/James Carr
  - "I Hear the Hogs in My Kitchen", 1962 (Box 5)
  - Rand, Christopher, "The Holy Land at Christmastime", 1963 (Box 5)
    designer/typographer Begg, John; printed by Oxford UP/ Marbridge Printing
  - Noel 1963 (to Wayne Yenawine) (Box 5)
    sent by Charlots, The
  - Painting/print collage; poem by St. Francis, 1963 (Box 4)
    sent by Neagoe, Anna; designer/typographer Neagoe, Anna
  - Kennedy, J.F, "The Place of the Artist in Society", 1964 (Box 5)
    sent by Blumenthal, J.; printed by Spiral Press
  - Shillito, Charles, "The Country Book-Club. A Poem", 1964 (Box 5)
    sent by Hall, G.K.; printed by Stinehour Press/Meriden
  - Heckscher, August, "A Plea for Books", 1966 (Box 5)
  - Decker, Peter, "Westering into Ireland", 1967 (Box 5)
    sent by Patterson, Jerry
  - Decker, Peter, "Westering into Scotland", 1968 (Box 5)
  - Anonymous Greek fragment., 1970 (Box 5)
    sent by Walker, Ralph
  - "Person & Place: A Canadian Garland", 1974 (Box 5)
  - The Season's Greetings, undated (Box 5)
    sent by Angelo, Valenti; designer/typographer Angelo, Valenti
  - Stein, Gertrud, "A Christmas Greeting", undated (Box 5)
    sent by Sans Souci Pr; designer/typographer Ferguson, William; printed by Sans Souci/Willliam Young
  - Season's Greetings "Little Iddens", undated (Box 5)
    sent by Cohn, Marguerite